[music]
Hello everyone and welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
My name is Catherine
and today we have a
very technical, very
advanced lesson for you.
This is all about one
of my favorite subjects.
That's right, we're
going to talk about music,
but specifically we're
going to talk about
the piano and learning
how to play the piano,
so we're going to talk about very
specific vocab related to this instrument.
Right, so piano and playing
music, not listening to music.
Right, so we're going to hear a lot
of interesting words and phrases here.
Some of them actually
come from foreign languages
like Italian, so listen
up, we'll be back in a
moment and when we
come back we'll be talking
about what these
words and phrases mean.
[music]
Hi Cody, how did practicing go this week?
Well, I had several tests
in an oral presentation
this week, so I didn't
get a chance to memorize
the second page, but I think
I mastered the tricky section.
Great, warm up with some
scales and arpeggios first.
[music] Good, good.
This week we're going
to keep the rhythm steady
when you play the last
part with 16th notes.
Now let's take a look
at this tricky section.
Charlene, before I
start, I was wondering if
it was okay if I put a
small crescendo in here
and then a deep crescendo
back to pianissimo again over here.
Hmm, it might work.
I'll have to hear it.
Show me what you've done.
[music] Not bad.
It was horrible.
I played it much better at home.
Well, it's just nerves.
Just play the right hand for now.
One, two, three, four, five, six,
tah, tea, triple E, tea, good, good.
Don't forget the accidentals.
The key signature says that note should
be a G sharp, but now it's a G natural.
Now add the bass
clef, you're going to fast.
Remember the tempo
for this piece is Andante.
[music] Is that better?
Yes, much better.
Watch where you lift your foot
off the pedal, what was that?
Sorry, the stretch for that
active is always hard to make.
That's okay.
Keep going.
You're moving ahead by leaps and bounds.
Watch your dynamics.
Keep your elbows lifted.
Remember to stroke the keys.
Don't pound.
That's better.
Remember that as a pianist or
any other musician you're technique
will be what separates
you from the pack just
as much or as more
so as your musicianship.
[music]
All right, we're back.
So you probably noticed
that there are a lot
of ways to describe certain
aspects of playing the piano.
They talked about
scales and all that stuff.
So why don't we take a deeper look at
this vocab in language takeaway part one?
Language takeaway.
Okay, so the first part of
the lesson is the warm-up.
That's when we, you know, start to get
our fingers moving and really stretch out.
This is an important part of any musician's
routine because it's also a way to practice
some very basic, very
fundamental things for
the first, the first
of which is a scale.
Okay, so actually Cody started
warming up with some scales.
So what exactly are scales?
Well, basically there are
different musical notes.
Some people know them as doe re mi fa solo
ti doe. Some people call them CDE FGABC.
But each of those and
many others have scales.
So that's eight notes together.
Okay, so basically when
you're playing scales,
you're just playing a
sequence of these eight notes.
Right, going up or down.
Okay, to warm up.
And what about in our peggio?
I think this is Italian, right?
Definitely.
Our peggio is another kind of warm-up
where you're not playing every single note.
You're playing some notes in a scale.
All right, so that's in our peggio.
Okay, very good.
So, and as you said, these
are usually for warm-ups, right?
Yeah, they're also very important
because they come into play later
when you're talking about the key
that a song or piece of music is in.
So this helps you memorize
the key that some music is in.
Okay, very good. So I
think related to to this
is the rhythm of the
piece that you're playing.
That's right, so rhythm
is really important.
Some people can even say, you know,
he's got rhythm or they have rhythm.
It's a way to describe the
beat of a kind of music.
So sometimes it has to do with
how fast or how slow something is.
Other times it has to do with the
way that the notes work together.
For example, a steady beat would be one,
two, three, four, one, two, three, four.
This is a complicated beat.
It goes, tah, tah, tah, tah,
tah, tah, tah, tah, tah, tah, tah.
So this is a very difficult kind of rhythm.
Okay, so the rhythm is just kind of, it
gives you the how fast, how slow it is.
And I guess if you
can take a look at notes
and you can play it in
many different rhythms,
but not necessarily, they're
going to sound correct.
Right, and actually it's interesting, in
English we also have a group of instruments
that are called rhythm instruments,
so this would be like the drums.
Okay, so it gives the beat.
Yes.
Very good.
And while moving on, I
think some other Italian
words popped up in here when they
talked about crescendo and de crescendo.
Right, so crescendo is when
something becomes louder.
So I can make a crescendo, right?
But a de crescendo, de in Italian, just
like in English, means it's the opposite.
So it means it's getting really softer.
Okay.
And what about panicimo?
Panicimo is basically an
indication, it also comes from Italian.
It's an indication that
a player or musician
should play something
very, very, very quietly.
It's almost like a whisper.
Okay, so all these three words
have to do with the volume of,
or how loud or not so
loud you play the instrument.
That's right.
Okay, very good.
And while moving on now,
we talk about accidentals.
Okay, this is important.
Remember earlier we
were talking about scales.
Well, for example, the
G scale has one sharp.
So that's an F sharp.
So if I'm playing it on the piano, there
are seven white keys and one black key.
Okay, so actually here, they mentioned G
sharp and then something like G natural.
All this, just like for everyone
that's out there is complete Chinese.
And we have no idea what this is all about.
So you have the accidentals
in G sharp and you're
describing something about
sharpness with accidentals.
That's right.
So basically, if you look at a
piano, you have white keys.
Right.
Those are, those are natural.
They don't have a sharp or a flat.
The sharps and flats are
actually played on the black keys.
Mm-hmm.
Usually it's a half step
from a normal note.
So G, it's a half step.
Okay.
We're talking about different keys.
So if something is in the
key of G, in all the music
people know what this is,
key of G, there's one accidental.
What's the accidental?
It's always F sharp.
And so an accidental means
a sharp or a flat in that key.
Okay.
And when we talk about sharps on the
piano, they're basically the black keys.
Yes, well, sharps and flats
can both be black keys.
Okay, very good.
And, well, apart from
accidentals in G sharp, G
natural, the teacher also
talked about a bass clef.
Okay, this is important for people who play
lower instruments like the bass, you know,
the upright bass, or people
who play the piano, obviously.
This represents a way
of writing the lower notes.
Okay.
Okay, so you see the lines, those five
lines on paper and people write the notes.
Well, sometimes they're for higher instruments,
you know, the flute or the trumpet.
But sometimes when
they're for lower instruments,
like the left hand
of a piano or for the
upright bass, you have
to write it in a special
register, a special part of
the sound kind of continuum.
And that's the treble.
That's the bass clef.
Okay.
So basically, if everyone
has ever seen piano
notes, it tells you what to play with
your left hand and your right hand.
So I imagine the bass
clef will be everything
that's on your left hand because
that sounds like deeper, greater, right?
Yeah, it's lower.
So it's lower on the scale, right?
Instead of like, a pie up here
where it's on the treble clef.
All right.
So the opposite would be the treble clef.
That's right.
The treble clef is up higher.
It's most other
instruments like the trumpet.
The bass clef is for lower instruments.
And that just means
that the way that you read
the music on the page
is a little bit different.
Okay, very good.
Well, we also got into things like tempo
and the piece it was described as Andante.
And Andante, this is a very Italian word.
Okay.
So Andante means that
something is played slowly.
Okay.
So apart from Andante,
so it's a style or a tempo, I
guess tempo is the speed
of which is played, right?
That's right.
But you're right to
say that it's also a
style because in many
symphonies, for example,
there's a movement, a part of the
symphony that's called the Andante.
And that's when everything starts
to get slow and serious or pretty.
I've heard, I don't know, in piano,
I've heard of something called staccato.
And I think this is also
related to tempo, right?
Staccato is the way
that you play something.
So instead of having
these long, pretty
notes, you're playing them
like this, the very very sure.
Right?
Like machine gun.
Okay.
So, but it's not related to the tempo.
It's kind of more just like the
way that you press the keys.
Exactly.
It's a style for playing.
Okay.
All right.
Well, the teacher also
told the student to be
careful where they lift
the foot off the pedal.
And the student said,
"Oh, I'm just so sorry.
The stretch for that octave
is always hard to make.
" Okay.
So an octave is really,
really important in music.
Like we were talking about earlier
with a scale, a scale is eight notes.
Well, the root, the place
the word octave comes
from is the number
eight, like an octagon.
So octave means eight notes together,
or like low C, high C, that's an octave.
Okay.
So think about the
piano when you're putting
your fingers on the
keys, covering eight
keys means you have to stretch your thumb
and you're pinky out really, really far.
And so he's saying, "Ah, sorry, it's hard
for me to do this because the octave, that
stretch is really
hard for me to get it.
" Okay.
So this is different from an eighth, right?
Well, it depends.
Are you talking about eighth note?
I don't know.
Because an octave is eight and
eighth note, so it's a different I imagine.
Yeah.
Well, you're heard in the
dialogue, 16th note, eighth note.
That's actually talking
about the length of a note.
How long you hold it?
Okay.
So basically, you're
saying it's the way you
measure the music,
you can have four count
or three count, but you
divide that into pieces.
It's like a pie in math where
you divide it into pieces.
So if it's a 16th note
or an eighth note,
that's the length based on
the kind of music you're playing.
So I imagine 16th note
is shorter than eight.
Yes.
Okay.
At least I got that one.
And 30 seconds note is
shorter than a 16th note.
Wow.
You have all the way up to 30 seconds.
64th note is short.
Oh, wow.
Okay.
It gets very complicated.
Very math-y.
All right.
And towards the end of
teacher recommended for
Cody to watch his dynamics, what
does she mean with watch your dynamics?
I used to get this all the time in music.
So you're concentrating on your music.
You're playing.
You're getting the notes and
Cody is stretching his hands.
The octaves are so far away.
And he forgets to play
it loud or soft because
on the page it says like we
heard earlier, day crescendo.
So get much, much softer.
So Cody completely forgot.
He's not listening.
He's not reading the page and seeing
what it says about the volume of the music.
So basically the
dynamics are like the
instructions of how loud to
play it or not, or not so loud.
Exactly.
So does it say pianissimo or the opposite?
Does it say forte?
Oh, so it actually say
this on the notes in forte.
I'll say that.
F-O-R-T-E or sometimes just F.
Okay.
So P is piano.
That means like we said earlier,
quiet, pianissimo is P.P.P. is very quiet.
F is forte.
Lauer.
Mm-hmm.
I think, well, if anyone out there plays an
instrument you can relate in, you can maybe
know about these, these things that
you may know it in your original language.
I know, I know many
people who play musical
instruments and don't really know the
technical words in their original language.
I mean, things like
Andante and pianissimo,
things like this, I think
are universal, right?
They're used in whatever language.
Exactly.
Very widely used.
But things like the accidentals or bass
clef or scales and stuff like that, I think
it's obviously different languages
in, for example, you know
Italian like scales or
accidentals or they're different.
They're different.
All of the other words.
So the instructions on
the page, because music
is shared all over the
world, the instructions
on the page are almost always in Italian,
so piano and Andante, or they're in German.
All right.
So music.
But everything else, scales, octaves,
these are all in your native language.
So they're very, very
important to study if
you want to play, and I think very, very
useful if you want to study an instrument.
Yeah, of course.
I think it's also very
good idea to just
have a general knowledge
about these things,
because, you know, it's sometimes
it's nice to know a little bit about it.
And maybe if a friend
is talking about music,
you can maybe understand a
little bit more about what it's like.
Or if you see music, a sheet of music, you
can now more or less know what's going on
with all those drawings
and little scribbles.
Absolutely.
And if you have any
questions, of course,
you're welcome to come
to our website and ask
or share your experiences as Marco has just
said, so please come to EnglishPod.com.
We hope to see you there.
All right.
We'll see you guys next time.
Bye.